<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="./schema/out/introdh_schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mathilda</title>
                <author xml:id="">Mary Shelley</author>
                <editor xml:id="">Javier Rosario</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unpublished test document</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Scan</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
           <opener> Chap. 1
            Florence. nov 9th. 1819</opener>
                <p>It is only four o'clock; but it is winter
                and the sun has already set. There are no
                clouds in the clear, frosty sky to <unclear>reflect</unclear> its
                giant beams, but the air itself is tinged with a
                slight <unclear>wreate</unclear> colour which is again reflected on
                the snow that covers the groud. I live in 
                a lone cottage on <add>a</add> solitary, wide heath: no
                voice of life reaches me. I see the desolate plain
                covered with white, save a few black patches
                that the noonday sun has made at the top
                of those sharp pointed hillocks <del>on</del> <add>from</add> which
                the snow, shiny as it fell, by thinner
                than on the plain ground: a few birds
                are pecking at the hard ice that covers the pools—
                for the frost has been of long continuance</p>
                
                <p>I am in a <del>mathilda</del> strange state of mind.
                I am alone—quite alone—in the world<unclear>.</unclear> The blight
                of misfortune has <unclear>hovered</unclear> over me and withered me.
                I know that I am about to die and <del>yet</del> I feel
                happy—joyious—I feel.—. I feel my pulse; its beats fast:
                I place my thin hand on my cheek; it burns: there
                is a slight, quick <unclear>spirit</unclear> within one which is now
                emitting its last sparks. I shall never see the snows
                of another winter—I do believe that I shall
                <del>v</del> never again feel the <del>urging</del> warmth of
                another summer sun; and it is <unclear>on</unclear> this per-
                <unclear>onasion</unclear>that I begin to write my tragic history.
                Perhaps a history such as mine had better
                die with me, but a<del>n</del> feeling that I cannot
                define leads me on and I am too weak both in
                body and mind to resist <del>ang</del> the slightest <unclear>mmgdre</unclear>
                <unclear>while</unclear> life was strong within me thought indeed
                that there was a sacred horror in my tale that
                rendered it unfit for utterance, and now about
                to die I pollute its mystic terrors. It is as the
                wood of the <unclear>Eumenides</unclear> none but the dying may
                enter and <unclear>corpus</unclear> is about to lie.</p>
            
                <p>What am I writing :— I must collect my thoughts.
                I do not know that any will peruse these pages
                except you, my friend, who will recieve them at my
                death. I do not <unclear>addep</unclear> them to you alone because it will
                give me pleasure to open <unclear>wpon vrea uoae guenavin in a wal</unclear>
                that would be needless if you alone read what I shall
                write. I shall relate my love therefore as if <del>it were</del> I
                wrote for strangers. You have often asked me the
                course of my solitary life; my tears; and above all of my
                impenetrableand <del>unaffected</del> unkind silence. In life I
                dared not; <del>I</del> in death I unveil the mystery. Others
                will top these pages highly over: to you, Woodville,
                kind, affectionate friend, they will be dear—the
                precious memorals of a heart-broken girl who,
                dying, is still wounded by gratitude towards you.
                Your tears will fall on the words that <unclear>record</unclear> my
                misfortunes; I know they will—and while I have
                life thank you for your sympathy.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
